A Guide to the Marietta Minnegerode Andrews Papers, (1941-1931)
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Marietta Minnegerode Andrews Papers (1914-1931)
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M189
1 linear foot.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the Department by Mrs. William R. (Emma Gray) Trigg, along with the Mary Sinton Leitch Papers (#52), in November 1968.
Biographical Information
Marietta Minnegerode Andrews was born 11 December 1869 to Charles and Virginia Cuthbert Minnegerode. She studied art in Washington, D.C., New York, Paris and Munich. In 1895, she married her former instructor, Eliphalet Fraser Andrews, director of the Corcoran School of Art in Washington, D.C. She began to write and publish poetry and prose after the death of her husband in 1915. Her works include Songs of a Mother (1917), Out of the Dust (1920), George Washington's Country (1930), and Many Waters (1931).
Scope and Content
The collection consists of approximately 100 items. The bulk of the material concerns Black Brother, a long, unfinished manuscript that Mrs. Andrews was working on when she died. Some of her notes and research materials are included, as well as seven of her short stories. There are two pages that have been identified as belonging to George Washington's Country.
Arrangement
The manuscript for Black Brother has been reconstructed from internal evidence and Mrs. Andrews' notes. Associated materials, probably intended for inclusion in the final book, have been arranged following the manuscript. Photographs have been removed to the University photograph collection.
Contents List
- Black Brother Section I 1850-1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Black Brother through introduction of Grandfather's story (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Black Brother Grandfather Wiltberger's Story (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Black Brother Frontispiece through John Brown Information (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Black Brother Section II 1860-1870 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Black Brother Section III 1870-1880 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Black Brother Section IV 1880-1890 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Black Brother Section V 1890-1900 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Black Brother Section VI 1910-1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Black Brother Section VII 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Black Brother Music pages (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Black Brother Draft (1 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Black Brother Draft (2 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Black Brother Draft (3 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Black Brother Portions (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Black Brother Portions (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Black Brother Miscellaneous Notes (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Black Brother Miscellaneous Notes (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Black Brother Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Short Life of Samuel Chapman Armstrong, Founder of Hampton Institute 1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Short Life of Samuel Chapman Armstrong, Founder of Hampton Institute 1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Clippings: Black politics n.d., 1929 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Black Brother Forward, Notes of Captain Gordon 1930 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Black Brother Notes of Captain Gordon 1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Black Brother Notes of Captain Gordon (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Black Brother Notes of Captain Gordon (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Anecdotes (1 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Anecdotes (2 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Anecdotes (3 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Draft "The Negro: His Place in Art as Creator or Subject?" (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Draft "On Sherman's March" (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "Among the Mormons" (1 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 13)
- "Among the Mormons" (2 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "Among the Mormons" (3 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 15)
- George Washington's Country (Box 2, Folder 16)
- "Joy Rides of a Poor Relation" (Box 2, Folder 17)
- "The Navajos" (Box 2, Folder 18)
- "On Other People's Gas" (Box 2, Folder 19)
- "Poking Around in Europe" (Box 2, Folder 20)
- "The Redemption of Moses" (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Draft "The Redemption of Moses" (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Untitled Short Story (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Clippings: Marietta M. Andrews (Box 2, Folder 24)